<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> Letter from Olof H Larsson to Amandus Johnson, 21 May 1935: TEI Transcription.</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcribed by</resp>
               <name>Charlotte Selander</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Borås</publisher>
            <date>7 June, 2022</date>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Borås</name>
               <name>Faculty of Librarianship, Information, Education and IT</name>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Allégatan 1</addrLine>
               <addrLine>501 90 Borås</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Sweden</addrLine>
               <addrLine>https://www.hb.se/en/staff/faculty-of-librarianship-information-education-and-it/</addrLine>
            </address>
               <idno type="project">Brev 11_2</idno>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://www.creativecommons.org//licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
               <p>Original letter and currently in  the public domain (Github). 
                  Transcription distributed under a CC-BY-SA 4.0 license</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>The original letter is in the hands of a distant relative of Ida Thoresen, Helena Nystedt, who
            has approved the use of the letters for this assignment.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Letter from Olof H Larsson to Amandus Johnson, 21 May 1935</title>
               <author>Olof H Larsson</author>
               <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
               <date>21 May 1935</date>
            </bibl>
          </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="letter">
      <body>
       <pb n="1"/>
        
        <opener>
               <dateline rend="text-align: right">  
                  <date when="1935-05-21">, May 21st, 1935</date></dateline>
                  <name ref="Olof H Larsson" type="person"></name> 
           <name>OHL/UR</name> <lb/> <lb/>
                    </opener> 
         <opener rend="text-align: center">  
            <persName><roleName>Dr.</roleName> <forename>Amandus</forename> <surname>Johnson</surname>,</persName> <lb/>
               <orgName> 
                  <orgName>John Morton Memorial Museum,</orgName>
                  <orgName> <lb/>
                     <name type="city"></name> <emph rend="underline">Philadelphia.</emph> <lb/>
                     <name type="state">Pennsylvania</name>
                  </orgName>
                </orgName>
       </opener> 
         <lb/>
         
                 <p>
                    My dear <roleName>Dr.</roleName> <surname>Johnson</surname>,<lb/> <lb/> </p>
                  
                  <p rend="inednt"> Your letter of the <date>16th of May</date> came to hand as I re-<lb/>
                  turned from a few days trip south and I am very sorry, indeed<lb/>
                  that I had no chance to meet you again and to continue the<lb/>
                  pleasant discussion we had when you were kind enough to visit<lb/>
                     me in my office.<lb/> <lb/> </p>
                    
                  <p rend="indent"> I am also sorry that we did not meet se that I could<lb/>
                  clear up the misunderstanding, on which your letter to me<lb/>
                  seems to be based. I tried to get hold of you over the te-<lb/>
                  lephone both in <placeName>Stockholm</placeName> and <placeName>Gothenburg</placeName>, 
                     but did not succeed.<lb/> <lb/> </p>
                  
                  
                  <p rend="indent"> Before I had an opportunity to write my answer I re-<lb/>
                  ceived a call from <roleName type="honorific">Miss</roleName> 
                  <surname>Thoresen</surname>. <emph rend="underline">I may mention that this<lb/>
                  was the first time I ever saw <roleName type="honorific">Miss</roleName> 
                  <surname>Thoresen</surname> or had any kind of<lb/>
                  communication with her in the above matter.</emph> This very charming<lb/>
                  lady was rather upset about your letter to me, of which you<lb/>
                  have sent her a copy. Since she had not done, what you seem<lb/>
                  to think she had, she was not afraid of your threats but very<lb/>
                  sorry, that you should suspect her. She told me, that she had<lb/>
                  never even had a thought, that you had tried to hold up the<lb/>
                  sale of her statue. On the contrary, she felt, that you had<lb/>
                  been very kind to her and done all that was possible to be of<lb/>
                  assistance to her, even if she was sorry, that you had not<lb/>
                  accepted the cheque from <roleName type="honorific">Mr.</roleName> 
                     <surname>Bendix</surname> in the first place.<lb/> <lb/> </p>
                  
                  <p rend="indent"> As for my part, I do not understand, why you got me<lb/>
                  mixed up in this matter. I have had nothing to do with it<lb/>
                  from beginning to end, received no letter from 
                  <roleName type="honorific">Miss</roleName> <surname>Thoresen</surname><lb/>
                  or anybody else about it and taken no action of any kind. It<lb/>
                  would be rather interesting to know, who could be the mischief<lb/>
                     maker, who has been telling you differently.<lb/> <lb/> </p>
                  
                  <p rend="indent"> I do not see, why things of this kind have to come<lb/>
                  up between you and me. As you are aware, I have sometimes<lb/>
                  differred with you in my ideas - and always plainly told you<lb/>
                     so - but I have never doubted the disihterested zeal, with<lb/> <lb/>
                 </p>
                
                <pb n="2"/>
                  <p rend="text-align: center">2.  <roleName>Dr.</roleName>
                     <forename>Amandus</forename> <surname>Johnson</surname>.</p> <lb/>
         
                  <p>
                  which you have pursued whatever cause you have thought right<lb/>
                  and I have always been under the impression, that this respect<lb/>
                     for you has been reciprocated.<lb/> <lb/> </p>
                  
                  <p rend="indent"> Instead of writing a letter like that, would it not<lb/>
                  have not been a good idea to get in touch with me or with 
                  <roleName type="honorific">Miss</roleName><lb/>
                  <surname>Thoresen</surname>, which would have cleared up the matter without this<lb/>
                  unnecessary correspondence. Incidentally would it not be<lb/>
                  wise not to believe everything that is told to you, when it<lb/>
                     must seem unreasonable, that it is true.<lb/> <lb/></p>
         
                  <p rend="indent"> I hope, that if there is anything I can do to assist<lb/>
                  you in the work, which we were discussing in our meeting here,<lb/>
                     you will let me know,<lb/> <lb/> </p>
                  
                     
                    <closer> In the meantime I remain, with kindest regards and <lb/>
                       best greetings,<lb/> <lb/>

                   
                        <salute rend="text-align: center">
                           Very sincerely yours.<lb/>
                        </salute>
                     </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
