<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Amandus Johnson to Ida von Schulzenheim, 03 June 1930: TEI
                    Transcription.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding by</resp>
                    <name>Sofia Rödström</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Charlotte Selander and Sofia Rödström</authority>
                <publisher>University of Borås</publisher>
                <date when="20220607"/>
                <distributor>
                    <name>University of Borås</name>
                    <name>Faculty of Librarianship, Information, Education and IT</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Allégatan 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>501 90 Borås</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Sweden</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>https://www.hb.se/en/staff/faculty-of-librarianship-information-education-and-it/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <idno type="project">Letter 1</idno>
                </distributor>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://www.creativecommons.org//licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                        <p>Original letter and currently in the public domain (Github).
                            Transcription distributed under a CC-BY-SA 4.0 license</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>The original letter is in the hands of a distant relative of Ida Thoresen,
                    Helena Nystedt, who has approved the use of the letters for this
                    assignment.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Previously unpublished letter. <respStmt>
                        <resp when="20220308">Facsimile created by</resp>
                        <name>Charlotte Selander</name>
                    </respStmt>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Letter from Amandus Johnson to Ida von Schulzenheim, 03 June 1930</title>
                    <author>Amandus Johnson</author>
                    <date>03 June 1930</date>
                    <lang>eng</lang>
                    <note> "eng", according to ISO 639-2 Code</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Examination assignment within the course Digitising Cultural Heritage Material
                    VT22.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Apparent errors have been marked as <sic/>, but correct readings not
                        provided.</p>
                </correction>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphens have been transcribed as they appear</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <p>The appearance of graphic figures are briefly described in prose.</p>
                <p>Shifts between handwritten and machine written type are marked with <handShift/>
                    .</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
            
        
    </teiHeader>


    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>

            <opener>
                <dateline rend="text-align: right">
                    <placeName>Nineteenth and Pattison Sts.,<lb/>
                        Philadelphia, Pa., </placeName>
                    <date when="1930-06-03"> June 3, 1930</date>
                </dateline>
                <persName rend="text-align: left"><roleName type="honorific"
                        >Miss</roleName> <forename>Ida</forename> <surname>von
                    Schulzenheim</surname>,</persName><lb/>
                <address>
                    <street>78 Riddaregatan</street>
                    <lb/>
                    <name>Stockholm,</name>
                    <country>Sweden.</country>
                    <lb/>
                </address>
            </opener>

            <p> Dear <roleName type="honorific">Miss</roleName> von
                <surname>Schulzenheim</surname>:<lb/> </p>
                <p rend="indent"> We have made considerable progress with the
                arrangements of the<lb/> exhibit. Last night men from <orgName>the Academy of Fine
                    Arts</orgName> worked here until<lb/> past ten o’clock and they are here this
                morning. I think they shall<lb/> finish hanging the pictures tomorrow. We have not
                followed your arrange-<lb/> ment at all, as <roleName>the President</roleName> of
                    <orgName>the Academy of Fine Arts</orgName> thought we<lb/> should place them in
                a manner that would suit American taste and be more<lb/> effective in displaying the
                pictures. The paintings alone fill up nine<lb/> rooms, as we have given them plenty
                of space. We have not as yet put up<lb/> the sculptures and the other things. I
                believe we shall not arrange the<lb/> textiles or the embroidery work, as that might
                fade in the sun, and I do<lb/> not believe that we should sell them this summer.
                Likewise, I believe we<lb/> shall keep the small things packed in boxes until the
                fall. It will be too<lb/> difficult to look after the little things when visitors
                come here. The<lb/> collection is insured against all risks, fire, theft, etc.</p>
            <p rend="indent">It seems that someone has made inquiries in <placeName>New York</placeName> about
                the con-<lb/> dition of the exhibit and what precautions have been taken against
                risks<lb/> etc. I did not tell <orgName>the Academy of Fine Arts</orgName> about
                this, for if they knew<lb/> about those inquiries they would probably not care to
                have anything further<lb/> to do with the exhibit. I would, however, advise you very
                strongly, not<lb/> to make inquiries from any other parties about this exhibit, if
                you want<lb/> us to handle it.</p> <p rend="indent">I am sending you a cable today, asking you to
                come over on <date>the 14th</date><lb/> if you can, to be with us on the
                    <date>24th</date>, when we have a sort of private<lb/> opening. You could stay a
                week and then go back on a Swedish boat. I<lb/> should like this very much, as we
                then could talk matters over concerning<lb/> prices and other points which are not
                very clear to us. We shall not<lb/> print the catalogue until the fall, but use a
                manuscript copy in the<lb/> sale of the Art. We have made no further effort to sell
                any more of<lb/> your paintings and pieces of sculpture and will not until I hear by
                letter<lb/> from you. However, we have had a number of inquiries. For instance,
                I<lb/> have a party who wants to buy <name>"The Windmill"</name> by
                    <surname>Akerman</surname>, and the <name>Landscape<lb/> in Scania</name>; but
                they have offered only <num type="ordinal" value="150.00">$150.00</num> for
                    <name>"The Windmill"</name> and<lb/>
                <num type="ordinal" value="175.00">$175.00</num> for the <name>Landscape</name>. I
                could not sell it for that as I do not know<lb/> if the artist would accept that
                price, especially since <orgName>the Academy of<lb/> Fine Arts</orgName> wants 15 %.
                If however, the artist is willing to accept those<lb/> prices, and we cannot get the
                price given in the catalogue, we shall sell<lb/> it to the party in question. Do not
                cable the artist’s decision on this<lb/> as there is time enough to write. I have
                the name and the address of the<lb/> party and can always get in touch with her. It
                is quite possible that<lb/> we get an offer for the full price that this lady will
                    pay the price you<lb/> have intimated, although she said she would not.</p> <p rend="indent"> On
                account of these conditions, it would be very desirable if you<lb/> could come here
                for about a week or two weeks. We could then have the<lb/> exhibit in fine shape in
                the fall. However, I am myself going to <placeName>Stockholm</placeName><lb/> this
                summer and hope to be there towards the end of July unless my Doctors<lb/> should
                forbid me to travel. Unfortunately I must go to the hospital tomorrow<lb/> or the
                next day for observation, as they do not seem to know what is the<lb/> trouble with
                me. They assure me, however, that I shall be out in about a<lb/> week or at the most
                two weeks and will be on my feet by the time we have our<lb/> annual meeting and
                private opening.<lb/>
            </p>
            <closer rend="indent"> Hoping that it may be possible for you to come here and with very best<lb/>
                wishes to you and your Society, I remain,<lb/>
                <salute rend="text-align: right"> Very sincerely yours, </salute>
                <signed rend="text-align: right"><forename>Amandus</forename> <surname>Johnson</surname>.</signed>
            </closer>

            <postscript>
                <signed rend="monogram, text-align: left">AJ:N</signed>
                <p>
                    <label>P.S.</label> I am sorry you did not send the original manuscript with
                    your English<lb/> translation as we fail to understand what you mean by your
                    phraseology in<lb/> one or two cases, for instance you say “wastecloset", so far
                    as I know there<lb/> is no such word in English and there could not be one. Do
                    you mean <foreign>"Skräp-<lb/> rum"</foreign> or
                        <foreign>"skräpkammare"</foreign>? In any event we could not use
                    "wastecloset"-- that<lb/> means nothing. Your translation of
                            <foreign><orgName>“Handarbetets Vänner"</orgName></foreign> is also
                    inaccurate<lb/> and a great many other terms will not do. However, I shall
                    revise the Eng-<lb/> lish but I wish you would send the original Swedish in case
                    you send any<lb/> other manuscripts. I am anxiously waiting for the ten pages of
                    History of<lb/> Swedish Art which will make the catalogue valuable and make it
                    easy to sell.<lb/> Beside I can find no portrait of the Crown Princess nor or
                    the other prin-<lb/> ces. </p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
